Blanchard, Duncan; Papers ua902.065
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Duncan Blanchard Papers
1789-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Blanchard, Duncan C.
ua902.065
35.8 cubic ft.
The Duncan Blanchard papers document Blanchards career as a research associate at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute and as a senior research associate at the State University of New York at Albany.
Biographical Sketch
Duncan Cromwell Blanchard was born on October 8, 1924 in Winter Haven, Florida. Soon after his birth, his family moved to the small Berkshire community of New Lenox, Massachusetts where he spent most of his childhood exploring the surrounding area. Despite his curiosity about the world around him, Blanchard never dreamed of becoming a scientist. His teacher at the one-room school house very rarely mentioned scientists or their work and instead dreamed of becoming a commercial artist.
In 1942 Dr. Blanchard graduated high school and though he dreamed of attending art school or college, these dreams were put on hold due to the war. Instead, Blanchard took a job with General Electric in Pittsfield, Massachusetts as an apprentice machinist. After a year, he decided to leave G.E. and took the admittance examine for the Navys V-12 Officer Candidate Program. Within the exam, students were instructed to choose three schools from a provided list that they would like to attend for Officer training. Dr. Blanchards list consisted of Harvard, Yale, and Princeton and, after passing the exam, was sent to Harvard. After completing his training at Harvard, the Navy then sent him to Tufts where they told him to study mechanical engineering and naval science.
Once his training was complete, in 1945, Blanchard received orders to report to the Anti-Aircraft Training center on the island of Guam. Despite enjoying his time in Guam, Dr. Blanchard felt like he was missing something. He realized what was missing when he started to read Great Men of Science by Grove Wilson. Reading this book allowed him to learn about all the great scientists and showed him what he truly wanted to do with his life. With this new knowledge, Blanchard quickly left the navy and returned to Tufts where he earned a Bachelor in Naval Science in 1945 and a Bachelor in Engineering in 1947.
After receiving his degrees from Tufts, Blanchard went to work for General Electric Research Laboratory in Schenectady, New York. His first position was in the Physics Test Program but in 1948 he was reassigned to Project Cirrus where he worked as research assistant. Through his work with Project Cirrus, Blanchard came to know Irving Langmuir, Vincent Schaefer, and Bernard Vonnegut.
While Blanchard enjoyed working at G.E., he left them in 1949 to return to graduate school at Penn. State University. That same year he returned to G.E. to participate in a graduate fellowship. In 1951, Blanchard graduated from Penn. State with a Masters in Physics and joined the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution. While working at the Woods Hole Institute, Blanchard served as a Research Associate from 1951-1963, and as an Associate Scientist from 1963-1968. During that time, he held a Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution Associates Fellowship from 1956-1958 and received his PhD from MIT in Atmospheric Science. Along with this work, Blanchard also served as a member of the Panel on Air-Sea Interactions for the National Academy of Sciences from 1963 to 1966. At Woods Hole Blanchards research interests focused on raindrop size, shape, stability and distribution in rain; basic mechanisms of the formation of warm rain; freezing phenomena; air-sea interaction with respect to the transfer of particulate matter and electrical charge; dynamics of collapsed bubbles in water; evolution of condensation nuclei from the sea; organic films on the sea and transport to the atmosphere; atmospheric and volcanic electricity; and the history of science.
In 1968 Blanchard rejoined Project Cirrus scientists Vincent Schaefer and Bernard Vonnegut as a senior research associate at the Atmospheric Science Research Center at the State University of New York at Albany. Besides Dr. Blanchard's research responsibilities, he also served as a professor in the Department of Atmospheric Sciences at SUNYA and was a member of number of professional organization such as the American Meteorological Society, the Electrostatics Society of America, and the American Association for the Advancement of Science. He continued to maintain close working relations with Leonard Woodcock, a colleague at Woods Hole, who later moved to the University of Hawaii.
Throughout his career, Dr. Blanchard was a prolific author. He published numerous scientific papers, technical reports, and articles. Along with that work, he also created educational films for the general public. He retired from SUNYA in November 1989 but continues to write. After his retirement, he published The Snowflake Man: a Biography of Wilson A. Bentley in 1998 and continued to write articles for the Wilson Bentley Newsletter up until March 2012.
Scope and Contents
Dr. Blanchards papers document his career as a research associate at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute and the State University of New York at Albany. The collection contains materials ranging from 1789 to 2003 with the bulk being from 1958 to 1989. The earliest materials in the collection are reprints of articles that he referenced for his research.
While some correspondence contains information about his personal life, the collection is focused on his professional career and research. Included in the collection are handwritten and typed notes, notebooks, journal articles, newspaper and magazine clippings, brochures, pamphlets, bulletins, memos, reports, correspondence, invitations, event programs, postcards, photographs, negatives, projection slides, drawings, graphs, figures, research data, drafts, rosters, applications, proposals, resumes, class outlines, grant outlines, and grant abstracts.
The documents are arranged in 4 series. Series 1 is arranged numerically while the remaining 3 series are arranged alphabetically. The series were arranged in this way to preserve Dr. Blanchards own arrangement scheme. Along with maintaining his arrangement scheme, his folder titles were also preserved. Folder titles were only changed if clarification was needed and some folders include dates that are in brackets. These bracketed dates reflect the dates that Dr. Blanchard assigned to the folders based on the date the material was published or presented at a meeting or conference.
For related materials, please see the following collections held by the ME Grenander Department of Special Collection and Archives: Atmospheric Sciences Research Center Records (UA450), which includes many publications and articles issued by the ASRC, Bernard Vonnegut (UA902.068), Raymond Falconer Papers (U-902.014) and Vincent J. Schaefer (UA902.010).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged in to four topical series.
Acquisition Information
The Duncan Blanchard papers were donated to M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Duncan Blanchard in 2002 with additional donations made in 2003 and 2004. 2002-2004 2002-2004
Related Materials
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the subject guide for Criminal Justice and Prisons.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted with the exception of select folders that are marked on the inventory. Researchers with inquiries about this material should consult and archivist.
Conservation and the Environment; Aerosols; Air--Microbiology; Atmospheric electricity; Atmospheric physics; Bubbles; Cloud physics; Drops; Electrostatics; History of science and technology; Lightning; Ocean-atmosphere interaction; Rain and rainfall.; Surface chemistry; Thunderstorm electricity; Volcanoes--Costa Rica; Volcanoes--Iceland; Volcanoes--Hawaii; Albany (N.Y.); Surtsey (island); Hilo (Hawaii); Irazu Volcano (Costa Rica); Administrative reports; Annual reports; Brochures; Charts; Correspondence; Drafts (documents); Field Notes; Laboratory Notes; Lecture notes; Manuscripts (document genre); Negatives (photographic); Newsletters; Newspaper clippings; Notebooks; Pamphlets; Photographs; Postcards; Research Notes; Rsums (personnel records); rosters; Slides (photographs); Technical reports; Transparencies; Video recordings; UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; Blanchard, Duncan C.; Hughes, Jim; Moore, A. D.; Moore, Charles B., 1920-2010; Schaefer, Vincent J.; Vonnegut, Bernard; Woodcock, Alfred H.; General Electric Company; State University of New York. Atmospheric Sciences Research Center; Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution; National Science Foundation (U.S.)
- Manuscripts, 1789-2003; 1; 9.8 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged numerically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 contains materials Dr. Blanchard published while at Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute and the State University of New York at Albany as well as after his retirement. The topics covered by these publications include the history of science, water-to-air transfer, aerobiology, sea salt aerosols, volcanic electricity, and surface charge. There are also materials covering his studies of bubbles, water droplets, and rain. Along with his scientific publications, Dr. Blanchard also wrote letters to editors, comments and replies to articles, book reviews, obituaries, and autobiographical articles. Dr. Blanchard published materials from the early 1950s to the early 2000s but the majority of materials in are from 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s.
  Included in the series are notes (handwritten and typed), notebooks, journal articles, newspaper and magazine clippings, brochures, bulletins, reports, correspondence, photographs, negatives, figures, data (handwritten), drawings, graphs, drafts, rosters, completed application and record forms, and resumes. Folders are arranged according to Dr. Blanchards own filing system with the exception that materials are arranged by the date of the materials included in the folder instead of the date the articles were published. Dr. Blanchards folder titles were also maintained unless further clarification was needed.
  - Waterfall electricity (1966), 1789; 1965-1966; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 1)
  - Wilson bentley's auroral observations (1983), 1864; 1881; 1885; 1961; 1974 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 2)
  - Wilson bentley's auroral observations (1983), 1978-1980; 1982-1984; 1986; 1993; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 3)
  - Bentley and lenard (1972), 1904; 1934; 1947; 1951; 1957 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 4)
  - Bentley and lenard (1972), 1962; 1966-1967; 1971-1973; 1977-1978; 1996 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 5)
  - Bentley and lenard (1972), Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 6)
  - references and unreferences (1974), 1916; 1969; 1973-1975; 1977; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 7)
  - electrically charged drops from bubbles in sea water and their meteorological significance (1958), 1938; 1955; 1957-1959; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 8)
  - Bubble foramtion and modification in the sea and its meteorological significance (1957), 1944; 1954-1957; 1963; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 9)
  - Condensation nuclei and the crystallization of saline drops (1964), 1946; 1950; 1960; 1963 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 10)
  - Condensation nuclei and the crystallization of saline drops (1964), 1980; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 11)
  - andrew Bunker 1916-1979 (1980) restricted, 1946; 1963; 1972; 1976; 1978-1980 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 12)
  - Andrew bunker 1916-1979 (1980), 1991; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 13)
  - vince schaefer at 70 (1977), 1947; 1959; 1965; 1967-1968; 1976 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 14)
  - vince schaefer at 70 (1977), Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 15)
  - Occ report 15, the distribution of raindrops in natural rain (1949), Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 16)
  - Occ report #16, the use of sooted screens for determining raindrop size and distribution (1949), Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 17)
  - Occ report #17, experiments with water drops (1949), Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 18)
  - The bentley flour technique fine screens for measuring drop sizes (1951), Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 19)
  - a verification of the bally- dorsey theory of spicule formation on sleet pellets 91951), 1951-1952; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 20)
  - raindrop size distribution in hawaiian rains (1953), 1951; 1953-1954; 1956; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 21)
  - Paper presented at radar weather conference, montreal sept. (1952), 1951; 1982; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 22)
  - a simple recording technique for determining raindrop size and time occurrence of rain showers (1953), 1952-1953; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 23)
  - The supercooling, freezing and melting of giant waterdrops at terminal velocity in air (1957), 1953-1955; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 24)
  - Papers on condensation nuclei and drop distibution during proj. shower (probulished in tellus)(1957), 1953-1957 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 25)
  - The production, concentration, and vertical distribution of the sea-salt aerosal (1980), 1953; 1978-1980; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 26)
  - Bernard vonnegut, the gentle iconoclast (1985), 1953; 1972; 1974; 1976; 1983 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 27)
  - Bernard Vonnegut, the gentle inconoclast (1985), 1989; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 28)
  - the bursting of bubbles at an air-water interface, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 29)
  - comments on "On the shape of water drops falling in stagnant air" (1955), 1954-1955; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 30)
  - electrified droplets from the bursting of bubbles at an Air-sea water interface (1955), 1954-1955; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 31)
  - Discussion of raindrop distribution made during project shower, Hawaii, 1954 (1957), 1954-1956; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 32)
  - a simple technique for the production of uniform sized droplets (1954), 1954-1955; 1957; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 33)
  - "Air bubbles in water"- A letter to the editor of th eamerican journal of physics (1956), 1955-1956; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 34)
  - "fingerprints of a storm" - article for oceanus (1956), Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 35)
  - The shape of a raindrop- pageant article (1956), Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 36)
  - Drawings of "elc. Of atm.." (1963), 1959-1960; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 37)
  - Drop size distributions produced by the breakup of large drops under turbulence (1973), 1959; 1966; 1972-1974; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 38)
  - The residence time of air bubbles 400 cm (1984), 1959; 1983-1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 39)
  - Thesis criticism (1961), 1959-1963; 1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 40)
  - Science, success, and serendipity (1979), 1959; 1966; 1979-1980; 1982; 1985 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 41)
  - Science, success, and serendipity (1979), 1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 42)
  - film drop production as a function of bubble size (1988), 1959; 1984-1988; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 43)
  - the size and height to which jet drops are ejected from bursting bubbles in seawater (1989), 1959; 1988-1989; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 44)
  - electrification of the atomsphere, mc-graw hill encyclopedia of sci and tech, 500 word article (1966,1980,1982), 1960-1961; 1979; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 45)
  - Atmospheric electricity and the oceans, oceanus article (1961), 1961-1962; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 46)
  - positive space charg from the sea (1966), 1961-1962; 1965-1966; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 47)
  - the surface of the ocean, sea frontiers article (1962), 1961-1962; 1967; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 48)
  - The vertical distribution of the concentration of sea salt in the marine atmosphere near hawaii (1984), 1961; 1982-1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 49)
  - the oceanic production of atmospheric sea salt (1985), 1961; 1984-1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 50)
  - progress in oceanography article (1963), 1961-1964; 1967-1968; 1978; 1989; Undated (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 51)
  - comments on the breakup of raindrops, J. atm. Sciences- 19, 119, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 52)
  - Meterological studies on the island of hawaii (1963), 1962-1963; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 1)
  - Sea to air transport of surface active material 91964), 1962; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 2)
  - charge seperation from saline drops on hot surfaces (1964), 1962-1966; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 3)
  - surface active organic material on airborne salt particles (from proc. Int. conf. ud phys. Toronto 1968), 1962; 1967-1968; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 4)
  - Condensation nuclei and raindrop spectra, a criticism of griffith's paper in J. atmos. Sci- 20, 198 (1963), Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 5)
  - yellowstone expedition (january 1964), 1963-1964; 1967; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 6)
  - encyclopedia of earth sciences articles on atmospheric electricity and on lightning (1967), 1963-1965; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 7)
  - electricity in volcanic clouds (1965), 1963-1964; 1967; 1979; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 8)
  - Oceanus article on volcano of surtsey (1st one- 1964), Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 9)
  - electrified volcanic clouds over surtsey (2nd oceanus article- 1966) (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 10)
  - Charge generation dure to contact of saline waters with molten lava (J. G. R. 1967 with S. B. and A. T. S), 1966-1968; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 11)
  - Nature and science article (museum of nat. history)-condensed from chap. 1-3 of D. C. B. books (1966), 1966-1967; 1974; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 12)
  - Water and the generation of volcanic electricity by d. Blanchard and S. Bjornsson (1967), 1967-1968; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 13)
  - experiments on the generation of raindrop-size distributions by drop breakups (1970), 1967; 1969-1970; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 14)
  - The oceanic production of cloud nuclei (1969), 1967-1970; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 15)
  - Ted rich (1979), 1968; 1978; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 16)
  - how to tell the truth (1971), 1969; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 17)
  - whitecaps at sea (1971), 1969-1971; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 18)
  - Production of water drops in the range of 6 to 10 mm dia (1971), 1970-1971 (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 19)
  - oceanic production of volatile cloud nuclei (1971), 1970-1971; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 20)
  - Mechanism for the water-to-air transfer and conc. Of bacteria 91970, 1970-1972; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 21)
  - variations in aitken and giant condensation nuclei in marine air (1972), 1970-1972; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 22)
  - Epidemioloy of mycobacterium intracellulare infection (1975), 1970-1976; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 23)
  - comments on "formation of a rain shower by salt seeding" (1972), 1971-1972 (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 24)
  - concentration of bacteria in jet drops from bursting bubbles (1972), 1971-1972; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 25)
  - borderland of buring bubbles (1972), 1971-1973; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 26)
  - the effervescence of ocean surf, 1972 (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 27)
  - reply to monahan's comment on "variations in ait ken-- marine aire" (1972), 1972-1973 (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 28)
  - surface water (1973), 1972-1973; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 29)
  - wilson bentley, pioneer in snowflake photomicrography (1973), 1972-1973; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 30)
  - letter to nature- biological regulation of climate (1987), 1972; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 31)
  - bubble tube: apparatus for determining attachment rate of bacteria to an air bubble rising in water (1974), 1973-1974; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 32)
  - on the truth behind the invention of the leyden jar (1975), 1973; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 33)
  - importance of bubble scavenging in the water-to-air transfer of organic material and bateria (1974), 1973-1975; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 34)
  - bubble scavenging and the water-to-wair transfer of organic material in the sea 91975), 1973-1976; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 35)
  - freshwater-to-air transfer of micro-organisms and organic matter (19770, 1973-1978; 1983; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 36)
  - electrostatic collection of jet and film drops (1975), 1974-1975; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 37)
  - summary and recommendations of nice symposium (1974), 1974-1975; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 38)
  - general statement by participants of the 2nd ind. Wea. Mod. Workshop (1975), 1974-1975; 1977 (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 39)
  - apparatus to determine the efficiency of transfer bacteria from a bursting bubble to the jet drops (1990), 1974-1977; 1988-1989; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 40)
  - enrichment of bacteria in film drops (1980), 1975; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 41)
  - north atlantic NRL report (1977), 1975-1976; 1981; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 42)
  - airborne pathogens (1977), 1976-1977; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 43)
  - comments on "Airborne sea salt sedimentation"(1977), 1976-1977; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 44)
  - nature's microtome: bursting bubbles at the surface of the sea (1976), 1976-1977; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 45)
  - aging and bursting bubbles in trace- contaminated water 91978), 1976-1978; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 46)
  - control of jet drop dynamics by organic material in seawater (1978), 1976-1978; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 47)
  - eight problems in bubble jet drop researches 91978), 1976-1978; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 48)
  - production of air bubbles of a specified size (1977), 1976-1977; 1979; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 49)
  - virus transfer from surf to wind, 1977 (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 50)
  - jet drop enrichment of bacteria, virus, and dissolved organic material (1987), 1977-1978; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 51)
  - tor bergeron and his "Autographic notes" (1978), 1977-1978; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 52)
  - dynamics of small bubble motion and bursting in freshwaters (1979), 1977-1979; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 53)
  - bubble scavenging of bacteria in freshwater quickly produces bacterial enrichment in airborne drops (1981), 1977-1978; 1980-1981; 1983; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 54)
  - the formation of hollow sea-salt particles from the evaporation of drops of seawater (1988)1978, 1986-1988; 1996; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 55)
  - enrichment of bacteria water (1979), Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 56)
  - grandpa and his flip-flopping snowflakes (1980), 1979-1980; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 57)
  - marine fog droplets and salt nuclei- part II (1981), 1980-1981 (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 58)
  - the lighter side of life with project cirrus (1981), 1980-1981; Undated (Box 2 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 59)
  - A gift to the AMS of Wilson Bentley's (1984), 1980-1981; 1984-1985; Undated (Box 3 (1-Manuscripts), Folder 1)